A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Director, Herbert Spencer Gasser, Biographical Material, Series 6 FA814
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Director, Herbert Spencer Gasser, Biographical Material, Series 6
1935-1961
Rockefeller Archive Center
Gasser, Herbert S. (Herbert Spencer)
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA814
22.2 Cubic Feet 45 boxes, 4 volumes, 2 packages
45 boxes; 4 volumes; 2 packages
Related Archival Materials note
Herbert Spencer Gasser was Director of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research 1935-1953. During his tenure he continued many of the administrative routines which had been established during the directorship of Simon Flexner. Thus, much administrative correspondence, in particular, matters dealing with personnel and administration of the physical plant are to be found in the papers of the Business Manager, Edric B. Smith, who served also, as Secretary of the Board of Trustees.
See FA137 Rockefeller University records, Business Manager, Subject Files, Series 3. See FA809 Rockefeller University records, Business Manager, Series 4.
Biographical/Historical note
Herbert Spencer Gasser, 1888-1963, physiologist, was Director of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, 1935-1953. His early work at the University of Wisconsin and at Washington University was done on circulation and respiration, including the mechanism through which the heart is accelerated in exercise and the rate of decreased oxidation in the respiratory center. Later at Washington University and at Cornell University Medical College his major interest was in the physiology of nerve, developing electrophysiological techniques through the development of vacuum tube amplification and the cathode ray oscillograph. In collaboration with Joseph Erlanger, also of Washington University, he developed an exhaustive determination of the constants of nerve fibers and the classification of nerve fibers in accordance with their properties. The two men shared the Nobel Prize in Medicine and Physiology in 1944 for this work.
Biographical Note
1888 Born July 5 Platteville, Wisconsin
1907 Graduate State Normal School of Wisconsin, Platteville
1910 A.B. University of Wisconsin
1911 A.M. University of Wisconsin
1911-1912 Assistant in physiology University Wisconsin
1912-1913 Instructor in physiology, University Wisconsin
1915 M.D. Johns Hopkins University Medical School
1915-1916 Instructor in pharmacology, University Wisconsin
1916-1918 Instructor in physiology, Washington University St. Louis
1918-1920 Associate in physiology, Washington University
1920-1921 Associate Professor in physiology, Washington University
1921-1931 Professor in pharmacology, Washington University
1923-1925 Study abroad: University College, London; National Institute of Medical Research, London; Sorbonne, Paris; University of Munich
1931-1935 Professor physiology, Cornell University Medical College New York, New York
1935-1953 Director, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, New York, New York
1953 June, retired as Director; returned to work in his laboratory; Member Emeritus RIMR
1963 Died May 11 New York Hospital, New York, N.Y. Cremated; ashes sent to sister. Interred family plot, Platteville, Wis.
Prizes
1944 Nobel Prize in Physiology and Medicine Shared with Dr. Joseph Erlanger
1954 Kober Medal, Association of American Physicians
Clubs Sigma Xi, Gamma Alpha, Alpha Omega Alpha, Century Club, Quadrangle Club
Honorary Degrees
1936 D. Sc. university of Pennsylvania
1940 D. Sc. University of Rochester
1940 LL. D. Washington University
1941 D. Sc. University of Wisconsin
1945 D. Sc. Columbia University
1947 LL. D. Johns Hopkins University
1947 D. Sc. Oxford University
1948 D. Sc. Harvard University
1949 Doctor Honoris Causa, Université Libre de Bruxelles
1949 Doctor of Medicine, Honorary. Université Catholique de Louvain
1953 Honorifique de docteur. Université de Paris
1959 D. Sc. The Rockefeller University
Served
1918 Pharmacologist, Chemical Warfare Service
1936 Johnson Foundation Lecturer, University of Pennsylvania
1937- Rockefeller Foundation Trustee
1937- Russell Sage Institute of Pathology. Board of Directors
1941- Princeton University. Dept. of Biology
1941-1944 National Defense Research Committee Division 9
1945 Research Board for National Security (Member)
1947 Massachusetts General Hospital, Scientific Advisory Committee
Member of American Societies, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Fellow, American Association for the Advancement of Science, Fellow, American Neurological Association (Associate Member), American Philosophical Society, American Physiological Society, American Society of Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics, American Society of Electroencephalography (Honorary), Association for Research in Nervous and Mental Disease, Association of American Physicians, Harvey Society (Councilor, Vice President, President), History of Science Society, National Academy of Sciences, Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine (Pres. 1937-1939), New York State Society for Medical Research (Active Member, 1952), Foreign Societies, Academie Royale de Médecine de Belgique, correspondence member, Accademia della Scienze dell'Istituto di Bologna, correspondence member, Asociación Médica Argentina, Honorary Member, Finnish Academy of Sciences, Honorary Foreign Member, Physiological Society (British) Honorary Member, Royal Society of Edinburgh, Honorary Member, Royal Society of London, Honorary Member, Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences, Foreign Member, Sociedad Argentina de Biologia, Honorary Member, Société Philomathique de Paris, Corresponding Member
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Herbert Spencer Gasser collection was deposited with the Rockefeller University Archives by The University.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 302-6
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from scholarly access. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Other Finding Aids
FA143 Rockefeller University records, Herbert Spenser Gasser, Correspondence, Series 2.
FA813 Rockefeller University records, Herbert Spenser Gasser, Subject Files, Series 4.
Arrangement
Primarily original order.
Scope and Contents
Documents awards, nominations, addresses, laboratory notes, correspondence and memoranda.
Medical sciences; Medical research; Viruses -- Research; Physiology; Princeton University; National Academy of Sciences (U.S.); Flexner, Simon
- Biographical material, 6; 22.2 Cubic Feet 45 boxes, 4 volumes, 2 packages.
  - Biographical summaries (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Prepared at Rockefeller Institute 2pp, 1947 July
    - Prepared for National Cyclopedia of American Biography by John Simon, assoc. ed. 4 pp, 1935 October
    - Carbon copy of typescript. Prepared for NCAB 3pp Carbon copy of security questionnaire for US Government, 1937-1938
    - List of Societies, typescript with copies of materials from various questionnaires, 1942; 6 pages
    - Information for Biographical Encyclopedia of the World, 1944; Typescript with handwritten note 4 pp.
    - Holograph biographical sketch for Les Prix Nobel 3pp, 1945
    - British Who's Who, 1945; Typescript carbon copy
    - Passport application. Social Security #089-26-4514, 1945; Typescript carbon copy, 2 pp.
    - Biographical material sent to General Education Board, 1951; Typescript
    - Biographical sketch, Typescript 3 pp. holograph 3 pp.
    - "Brief Biographical sketch of Herbert Spencer Gasser", 1935 October 7; Typescript carbon copy
    - Draft of press release on retirement as Director of RIMR, 1953 June 18; 2 pp. typescript and 2 pp. duplicated copy
    - 1 volume Experimental Neurology, supp. 1, 1964 an autobiographical memoir with introduction by Joseph Hinsey, M.D. who was nominated to receive the Peter Coin
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes bibliography. Bound.
    - correspondence with T.I.A.A.; Curtis, Belknap and Webb; Equitable Life Insurance Society regarding beneficiaries, use of Nobel Prize money for neurophysiological research and start of retirement benefits, 1943-1953; 7 items
    - Bibliography 11 pages
  - Appointments and Awards, 1936-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Correspondence Alphabetical.
    - Académie Royale de Médecine de Belgique. Dec. 1947 admitted as Honorary Foreign Member, 1947 December; 2 items
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences. 1948 May 18 acknowledgement of election as Fellow, 1 item
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science. 1949 Aug. 29 request that HSG serve on Honorary Reception Committee, 1949 August 29; 2 items
    - American Neurological Association. 1956 elected Honorary Member, 2 items
    - American Philosophical Society. 1937 April 23-10 June 1943 Election as member and election as Councilor, 1937 April 23-1943 June 10; 7 items
    - American society of Electroencephalography. 1947 Made an Honorary Member, 2 items
    - Asociación Médica Argentina. 1942 October-June 30, 1943 Honorary Membership, 1942 October-1943 June 30; 4 items
    - Association for Research in Nervous and Mental Disease. 1941 January 15 Membership, 11 items
    - Association of American Physicians. 1937 May 12 Elected to membership, 2 items
    - Atomic Energy Commission. 1947 signed David E. Lilienthal, 2 items
    - Child Neurology Research Council. 1936 September-December. To serve on Advisory Committee, 5 items
    - Columbia University. 1945 Sc. D. Honorary, 4 items
    - Harvard College. 1948-1949 Sc. D. Honorary. Appointed to Committee to visit Medical and Dental Schools, 6 items
    - Johns Hopkins University. 1947 Apr. LL. D. Honorary, 1947 April; 2 items
    - Massachusetts General Hospital. Apr. 1947 Serve as member on Hospital's Scientific Advisory Committee, 1947 April; 2 items
    - National Academy of Sciences. Chairman of section on Physiology and Biochem. Chairman John J. Carty Fund Committee [see RG 302. 2 (1)] Nominating Committee for Vice Presisent and Council Members, 1942 April 28-1 February 1949 April 1945; 5 items
    - Nobel Prize. October 1944-January 1945 Telegram, letter announcing award. 2 from HSG, 1944 October-1945 January; 4 items
    - Oxford University. 1947 May Sc. D. honoris causa, 2 items
    - Princeton University. 1944 Reelected to advisory Council Department of Biology; 3 yrs from July 1, 1944, 2 items
    - Reale Accademia della scienze dell'Istituto di Bologna. June 1948. Corresponding Member, Class of Phys. Sci, 2 items
    - Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research. 1944, 1949 Elected to Executive Committee of Board of Trustees, 2 items
    - Royal Society of Edinburgh. July-September 1943 Elected Honorary Fellow; diploma sent, 1943 July-September; 4 items
    - Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences. March 1946 K. Vetenskapsakademiens matriculated among Foreign Members. Diploma, 1946 March; 3 items
    - Sociedad Argentina de Biologia. April 1936 Elected corresponding member. Letter signed A. Houssay, 1936 April; 3 items
    - Société de Biologie, Paris, 1954; 2 items
    - Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine. 1936 April 16 elected member of the Council, 2 items
    - Suomalainen Tiedeakatemia (Finnish Academy of Sciences). May-July 1947 Elected Foreign Member-Diploma, 1947 May-July; 4 items
    - Université catholique de Louvain. 1949 Honorary Doctor of Medicine, 4 items
    - Université de Paris. Jan. 1954 Souvenis photographs of degree of "Honorifique Docteur", 1954 January; 2 items
    - Université Libre de Bruxelles. 1949 Docteur Honoris Causa Faculté de Médecine et de Pharmacie, 5 items
    - University of Pennsylvania. 1936 Sc. D. honorary, 4 items
    - University of Rochester. February-June 1940 Sc. D. honorary Wallace and Clara Fenn as hosts, 1940 February-June; 7 items
    - Washington University, St. Louis. April-May 1940 LL. D. honorary, 1940 April-May; 8 items
    - Wisconsin University. clipping July 1941 Sc. D. honorary, 1941 July; 1 item
  - Letters of congratulation, 1935-1945; 69 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Arrangement note
    Arranged in chronological order.
    - Letters from colleagues
      Includes congratulations on occasions such as becoming Director of RIMR, or on the receipt of honorary degrees, or letters of sympathy received at the death of Dr. Stockard, or thank you letters for congratulations sent to others, or for reprints and from Trustees for the 1939 Review prepared for JD Rockefeller, Jr. [see RG 489 v. 28, 1940. Typescript signed; typescript carbon copies; some holographs.
  - Nobel Prize Award (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Anniversary Dinner 1941, Program; 1942 Addresses and announcement of motion picture "The Spirit of Nobel" mimeographed sheet with 1941, 1942, 1943 programs
    - Copy of cablegram announcing Gasser/ Erlanger Award, 1944 October 27
    - Science Service, 7 items for newspapers, 1944 October 28-30
    - Memo of phone call from Hjordis Swenson on arrangements, 1944 November 1
    - Swenson to HSG: thank you, 1944 November 1
    - Nabeth Hedin to HSG Am/Swedish News Exchange, 1944 November 14
    - Invitation to AM. /Scand. luncheon, 1944 November
    - Swenson to HSG Nobel Committee arrangements nd Memorandum to Nobel Prize winners, 1944 November 27
    - Henry G. Leach to HSG instructions for meeting, time schedule, broadcast, 1944 December 2
    - HSG to Swenson, copy of dinner address with covering letter nd Invitation Am/Scand Found, to participate in luncheon for Nobel winners 1944 Dec. 10, 1944 December 5
    - HSG to Henry G. Leach with broadcast address, 1944 December 7
    - HSG to John Watkins with speech changes, 1944 December 8
    - Seating list for presentation luncheon, 1944 December 10
    - Copy of HSG remarks at luncheon, 1944 December 10
    - Typed copy of tentative dinner program, 1944 December 10
    - Forum: "Education for Peace" remarks by HSG at dinner, 1944 December 10
    - thank you from HSG to N. Hedin for The Nobel Prizes by F. Henriksson, 1944 December 14
    - Swenson to HSG permission to publish "Education for Peace", 1944 December 15
    - N. Hedin to HSG no available publication on Nobel organization, 1944 December 15
    - Photographic print of Nobel citation to J. Erlanger, 1944?
    - Request to HSG for photo and biography for "Les Prix Nobel", 1945 May 22
    - H. Wistrand to HSG on arrangements; to forward "Les Prix Nobel" materials, 1945 June 28
    - HSG secretary to H. Wistrand acknowledging letter of 28th, 1945 June 30
    - HSG to H. Wistrand with 2pp. biography, 1945 July 13
    - speech given in Stockholm, 1945 December 10; Typescript carbon, 2 pp.
    - Arne Holmberg to HSG letter and proof sheets of Nobel lecture "Mammalian Nerve Fibers", 1946 February 26
    - HSG to A. Holmberg returning proof sheets, 1946 March 6
    - H. Swenson to HSG. Invitation to Nobel dinner on Dec. 10, 1946 November 5
    - Swenson to HSG. Regret Gasser unable to attend Nov. 8 reception; includes program, 1946 November 21
    - HSG to Swenson. Regret unable to attend dinner, 1946 November 23
  - Nobel Prize congratulations
    Alphabetically arranged with notes on acknowledgement which emphasize HSG's pleasure that Nobel Prize recognizes pure and basic research in the stressful time of practical needs. Some items marked "ans. 1. h. [long hand?] and no copy of reply is available. Listing below is incomplete.
    - A-G (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Avery, O.T. holograph
      - Auer, John holograph
      - Bard, Philip holograph
      - Bergmann, Max holograph
      - Bronfenbrenner, Jacques holograph
      - Bowman, Isaiah
      - Cohn, Alfred E.
      - Cole, Rufus holograph
      - Compton, Arthur holograph
      - Cori, Carl holograph
      - Fenn, Wallace C. holograph
      - Francis, Thomas holograph
      - Fulton, John
      - Gerard, R.W.
      - Graham, Helen
      - Gray, George W.
        From The Rockefeller Foundation including a draft of an article on Nobel winners and the aid they have received from the Foundation. Includes a reply by HSG stating the importance of Foundation aid.
      - Grundfest, Harry
    - H-M (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Hartline, Keffer holograph
      - Heidelberger, Michael holograph
      - Hill, A.V.
        Includes request for opinion on Donald Sheehan.
      - Houssay, Bernardo A.
        Includes signatures of 4 others.
      - Jacobs, Walter A. holograph
      - Jasper, Herbert H.
      - Jewett, Frank B.
      - Johnson, Warren C.
      - Lauffer, Max A. holograph
      - Lehmann, Jörgen
      - Levene, Ann (Mrs. P.A.T.) holograph
      - Liddell, E.G.T.
      - Liljestrand, G.
      - Lloyd, David holograph
      - Loeb, Leo
      - Malloch, J.G. holograph
      - McLean, Franklin C.
      - Meek, Walter J. holograph
      - Minot, George R. holograph
      - Morgan, Isabel holograph
    - N-Z (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Nachmansohn, David
      - National Broadcasting Co.
      - Nelson, Erwin E. (Am. Soc. for Pharmacology and Exp. Ther)
      - Northrop, John H. holograph
      - Odoriz, J.B. holograph
      - Olitsky, Peter holograph
      - Olmstead, J.W. holograph
      - Oppenheimer, B.S. holograph
      - Osterhout, W.J.V. holograph
      - Ozario de Almeida, Miguel
      - Page, Irvine H.
      - Parker, G.H. holograph
      - Parran, Thomas
      - Pick, Ernst P.
      - Platt, J.D.
      - Prentis, H.W. Jr.
      - Queen, Frank B. holograph
      - Quick, Armand J.
      - Rappleye, Willard C.
      - Ravdin, I.S.
      - Rheinstein, Adele
      - Rheinstein, Alfred
      - Richards, Newton holograph
      - Rivers, Thomas M.
      - Robertson, Albert D. holograph
      - Robinson, G. Canby holograph
      - Rockefeller, John D. Jr.
      - Rockefeller, Nelson
      - Rothen, Alexandre holograph
      - Rous, Peyton holograph
      - Rowntree, L.G.
      - Ruebhausen, Oscar M.
      - Sabin, Albert holograph
      - Sarnoff, Michael
      - Sawyer, W.A.
      - Scharrer, Ernst and Berta holograph
      - Schlesinger, R. Walter
      - Schmidt, Carl F.
        Holograph — includes a wish to push the nomination of A.N.R. Richards.
      - Schmitt, Francis O. telegram
      - Schreiber, George holograph
      - Sendroy, Julius, Jr.
      - Shaffer, Philip A. holograph
      - Shope, Richard E. holograph
      - Simpson, Lilly May
      - Skipper, Howard
      - Smillie, E.W.
      - Smith-Peterson, M.N. holograph, 2 notes
      - Snedeker, T.G.
      - Somoffi, Michael
      - Sormani. E.J.
      - Sperandeo, Elsie Carl holograph
      - Stadie, William C.
      - Starch, Daniel
      - Stanley, Wendell M. holograph
      - Stoll, Norman R. holograph
      - Strode, George K.
      - Stuck, Walter G.
      - Sulzberger, Marion B. holograph
      - Swift, Homer F. holograph
      - Taliferro, W.H.
      - Taussky, Hetha H.
      - TenBroeck. Carl holograph
      - Thomas, Charles C.
      - Thomas, Sadie R.
      - Tiselius, Arne
      - Trask, Lillia M.D. holograph
      - Van Slyke, Donald D. holograph
      - Wallace, H.B. For Washington University includes Resolution adopted by University
      - Weiss, Paul Alfred holograph
      - West, Ruth and Esau holograph
      - White, Philip and Caroline holograph
      - Wiggers, C.J.
      - Wilbur, Ray Lyman
      - Wildermuth, Ernest F.W. holograph
      - Wilson, Frank N.
      - Yerkes, Robert M.
      - Young, Hoylande D. holograph
  - Nobel nominations (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Code of Statutes", 1943 1946
    - nomination of Alfred Newton Richards, 1946-1947
    - nomination of Oswald Avery, 1952-1953
    - suggestion for award to Vincent du Vigneaud, 1955
    - (3) from Nobelstiftelson disavowing any connection with publication proposals of Stig Haglund, 1950 1956
  - Clippings and articles about Nobel Prize (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Messages for Press Conference, 1944 October 27
    - "Nerve activity research" by Herbert S. Gasser in Science News Letter 1944 November 11 p. 309 (3 cop)
    - "U.S. Physiologists win Nobel Prize" in Life 1944 November 13 p. 115
    - "Nobel Prize for Physiology and Medicine for 1944: Prof. J. Erlanger and Dr. H.S. Gasser" in Nature 1944 November 14
    - "1944 Nobel Prize in Medicine to Dr. Erlanger" in The Alumni Bulletin (Washington University) 1944 November p. 4
    - "Personalities in the News" Think 1944 p. 4
    - "The Nobel Prize in Physiology and Medicine for 1944" Journal of Neurophysiology 6 (1944) p. 325-326
    - "Medicine" Time 1944 Nov. 6 p. 88, 90, 1944 November
    - "Nobel Prizes" by Victor O. Freeburg in The American Swedish Monthly, 1944 December 14-15 1944 December 25
    - "Six Nobel Winners Receive Prizes at Gala Ceremonies" by Victor O. Freeburg in The American Swedish Monthly 1945 Jan. p. 14, 22 (2 cop)
    - Newspaper clippings (photocopies)
  - Memorabilia (Box 2)
    - Receipted bills 1942-1950 of expenses incurred for professional costs such as travel and contributions for memberships (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Photographs, 1935-1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Includes a copy print of 1911 Medical History Seminar at the University of Wisconsin; some informal leisure time snapshots (place and year not identified); formal Bachrach photograph (many prints); 1959 informal laboratory snaps; 1959 Rockefeller Institute Commencement photographs; 1963 photo at the University of Wisconsin; 1953 honorary degree ceremonies at University of Paris; photo of portrait painted by Robert Oliver Shemp, undated.
    - Photographs from office (originally framed) (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Lord Adrian pencil drawing signed Initialed MG, 1948 May
      - Ragnar Granit, signed, undated
      - A.V. Hill 1936, signed and dated in pencil
      - Print of "Tomb of David" Jones Wood, NY 1857 67th Street and East River
      - Photo of Gallego, 1956
        Includes two others not identified. Inscribed to Herbert Gasser, signed 1956.
      - Photo W.H. Howell, inscribed and signed, undated
      - Photocromo offset of B.A. Houssay Inscribed and signed, undated
      - Photo of Ali Monnier (University of Paris) Inscribed and signed, undated
      - Photo of C.R. Stoddard, unsigned undated
      - Printed translation: "Bequest of Pavlov to the academic youth of his country" Written just before his death at 87 years, 1936 February 27
      - Photo of Walter J. Meek, signed, undated
      - Photo of H.H. Dale, attached signature, undated
      - Photo: group of honorary degree recipients at Harvard Commencement, 1948. All identified
      - Photo of Joseph Erlanger, signed, 1937
      - Portraits (3) not identified
    - Framed drawing of a nerve. [Drawn by Ramon y Cajal] (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Appointments and honors record, 1936-1953; Typed on 26 3 × 5 index cards (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Record of Addresses, 1936-1950; Typed on 6 3 × 5 index cards (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Medals (packed and labeled individually) (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - #1 13th International Physiological Congress 1929 Boston
      - #2 Société Philomathique de Paris H.S. Gasser Membre correspondant
      - #3 20th International Physiological Congress 1956 Bruxelles (Congressus Universus Physiologial vicesimus)
      - #4 International Physiological Congress 1923 Edinburgh
      - #5 Conventus Physiologorum Internationalis 1923 Stockholm Duodecimus Holmiae
      - #6 15th International Physiological Congress 1935 Moscow CCCP